What are you thinking about?
何を考えてる？
Nothing.
別に
Why do I smell something burning?
何か焦げ臭くないな
My dish!
私の料理が！
Did something happen?
何があったのか
Qianqian wants to invite you to be her husband.
浅姉さんがあなたに 婿になって欲しいって
What?
何ですって？
She sees a good catch and now she wants to snatch him away, huh?
うまい話には すぐ食いついてくるのね
No, she means to "borrow" him.
借りるだけだって
To drive away a customer who's been harassing her.
しつこい客を追い払うために
That won't work, either.
借りるのもダメだわ
Dear, why are you pulling me?
あなた 何で引っ張ってるの？
If a woman wanted to borrow you from me,
もしほかの女子が あなたを借りると言ったら
would you be okay with it?
喜ぶの？
Well, if she were gentle, I guess I wouldn't mind.
優しい人なら 悪くもないな
Say that again! I dare you!
もう一回言ってみて
What kind of reward did she offer
彼女に何かもらったのか
that you'd sell me out just for a few taels of silver?
銀貨数両で私を売ったのか
How could I possibly sell you out for just a few taels?
銀貨数両で売るわけないでしょ
Yeah, exactly.
そうよ
A few taels do sound a bit too cheap.
数両だけでは安すぎる
Thirty taels.
三十両もらった
-What? -Thirty taels?
- 何ですって？ - 三十両？
Well, Changyu means well, after all.
長玉も他人を助けるためだね
Yan Zheng, why don't you just help out?
言正 助けてあげたらどう？
Think of it as doing a good deed.
徳を積むことにしよう
Hey, wait...
ちょっと
What? Why "hey, wait?"
「ちょっと」じゃないわよ
If you could sell for even 3 or 5 taels,
あなたが三　五両で売れるなら
I'd agree immediately.
直ちに応じるわ
You...
あなたって
Changning.
長寧
Let's go. Let's ignore them.
行くぞ ほっとけ
Turns out I'm worth even less than a pig.
叔父さんは豚一頭の 価値もないなんて
And how much do you think you're worth?
あなたはいくらの価値が あるんだと思う？
Why don't you ask someone else?
なぜ他人に頼まないのか？
Like that... Lord Li or whatever.
例えば李大人とか
Well, he's not in Lin'an.
彼は林安にいないもの
Even if he were, I wouldn't ask him.
いても頼まないわ
I've got my own husband—
自分の夫に頼まず
why go to an outsider?
なぜ他人に頼むの？
Just help Qianqian out.
浅姉さんを助けてあげて
It's just for 1 day.
一日だけだわ
If her Yixiang Restaurant goes under,
溢香楼が潰れたら
our business will suffer as well.
私たちの商売も やりにくくなるでしょ
That rice merchant surnamed Qi
あの斉という米商は
clings to her like a stubborn bandage.
しつこくて
He's just impossible to get rid of.
一度張り付いたら なかなか剥がれないの
Harmless, but irritating.
害はないけど 人の気持ちを悪くするよ
The rice merchant surnamed Qi?
斉という米商？
Who has he been associating with lately?
最近誰かと親しくしているのか
It's said to be a rice merchant from the Capital, surnamed Qi.
京城から来た 斉という米商らしいです
Just for 1 day?
一日だけ？
Just for 1 day.
一日だけ
[Pursuit of Jade]
[逐玉]
[Episode 13]
[第13話]
[Welcome guests from far and wide]
[客達九州]
This way, please.
どうぞこちらへ
Zheng.
義弟さん
In this outfit, let alone a restaurant manager—
その格好なら店主どころか
you could even pass for a marquis.
侯爺だと言っても信じられますよ
Not bad. This way, please.
いいわ こちらよ
I'm counting on you today.
今日は頼んだわよ
Rest assured.
任せてくれ
Changyu said
長玉が言った
you're her best friend in Lin'an.
あなたが林安で一番の親友だと
If she wants to help you,
彼女があなたを助けたいなら
I'll do it without hesitation.
俺も力を尽くすぞ
This way.
こちらよ
[Heaven-class]
[天字號]
Mr. Qi.
斉若様
Manager Yu, are you feeling better?
俞店主 体は大丈夫ですか
Mr. Qi, this is my husband, Yan Zheng.
斉若様 こちらは夫の言正です
He's been away on business recently.
近頃はずっとほかの ところで用事を済まして
He just returned to Lin'an today,
今日は林安に戻りました
and I brought him here specifically
うちのことで お世話になっておりますので
to thank you for supporting our humble restaurant's business.
夫を連れてお礼に参りました
Mr. Qi.
斉若様
Pleasure to meet you.
お世話になりました
So you're Manager Yu's husband.
あなたが俞店主の旦那さん？
Naturally.
その通りです
Yan Zheng, have a good chat with Mr. Qi.
言正 斉若様とゆっくりは話して
I'll go prepare some food and wine.
私は酒と料理を用意してきます
Mr. Qi.
斉若様
Please.
どうぞ
When Master throws his cup as a signal,
館様の合図で
that's our cue to tie that guy up.
奴を捕らえろ
I heard you came from the Capital, Mr. Qi.
斉若様が京城から来たと 聞きましたが
I wonder why you've come to our tiny Lin'an Town
なんでこの小さな林安鎮に
for grain business?
穀物の商売をしに来たんですか
Mr. Yan, you're not a local here either.
言若様もここの出身ではないだろ
So why are you running a restaurant here in Lin'an?
なんで林安で 料理店の商売をしてるのか
My wife may not have attended to things properly.
妻の不行き届きで
Please bear with us, Mr. Qi.
若様にはご迷惑をかけました
Next time there's business,
今後の商売は
please come straight to me.
私に任せてください
It's just I wonder how big a deal you can handle, Mr. Yan.
言若様は どれくらいの商売ができるのかな
For example...
例えば
200,000 piculs of grain.
二十万石の穀物はどうですか？
Pardon me.
失礼しました
With our Yixiang Restaurant doing so well,
この溢香楼はあまりに 繁盛しているもので
it's inevitable that some jealous rivals
嫉妬した同業者が
cause trouble in the dark.
邪魔をすることもあるんです
No wonder Manager Yu
なるほど 俞店主が
turned down my request to book the whole place earlier.
貸し切りの申し出を断ったわけだ
Apparently, my business wasn't enough to interest you guys.
商売が小さいからな
Alright then.
分かった
Let's talk another day.
ではまた話し合おう
Where is he?
あの人は？
Gone.
行った
Gone?
行ったの？
He gave up just like that?
こう簡単に諦めたとは
Zheng.
義弟さん
My 30 taels were really well spent.
三十両の価値はあるわね
What happened, Master?
館様はどうしたんですか
You won't believe it—
絶対思えないだろ
I just ran into a dead man,
余は死んだ人に出会った
and that woman actually claimed he was her husband.
彼が自分の旦那だとあの女が言った
Master, you mean...
館様が言ったのは
Marquis of Wu'an, Xie Zheng.
武安侯謝征のことですか
Xie Zheng?
謝征？
Isn't he dead?
彼が死んだじゃないんですか
If the Marquis of Wu'an is still alive,
もし武安侯が生きていれば
I'm afraid Lord Changxin's plan won't go smoothly.
長信王の策はうまく進まないでしょ
That smart father of mine
余の偉大なる父王は
intended to use the move of bandits stealing military grain
山賊に兵糧を襲わせた後で
to drive out refugees and create panic,
流民を追い立て 騒ぎを起こし
and then finish the operation.
そして締めくくるつもりだった
But now,
でも今は
not only is the Marquis of Wu'an not dead,
武安侯は死んでおらず
but he even knows we purchased 200,000 piculs of grain.
余らが二十万石の食糧を 買ったことまで知っている
Obviously, he's been prepared all along.
明らかに奴は計画を立ててた
It's still hard to say who will win in the end.
勝敗の行方はまだ分かない
This game is getting more and more interesting.
この芝居は ますます面白くなってきた
Back then, you intentionally leaked information, Master,
あの時館様がわざと噂を流し
to lead the Marquis of Wu'an to investigate
武安侯に
the Jinzhou Massacre from 16 years ago
十六年前の瑾州の惨事を 突き止めさせました
because you believed Prime Minister Wei wouldn't allow him to reopen the case.
それは魏丞相が再調査を 許さぬと思って
Your plan was to use Prime Minister Wei
彼の手で
to get rid of that serious threat Xie Zheng.
重大な脅威の謝征を 始末するためでした
But now, he's still alive...
しかし奴は生きています
Should we reveal his whereabouts
奴の居場所を
to Wei Yan in secret
魏厳にこっそり知らせ
and try to get Wei Yan to do the dirty work for us again?
再び魏厳の手を借りて 彼を殺しますか
No.
いいえ
I tried to turn them against each other back then
彼らを反目させたのは
just to sever Wei Yan's support.
魏厳の右腕を奪うためだ
The Marquis of Wu'an has never been our enemy.
武安侯は元々我々の敵ではない
Now that the rift between uncle and nephew is a done deal,
今や叔父と甥の不仲は決まりだし
and the Marquis of Wu'an has been cast out to the countryside,
武安侯も落ちぶれたので
we can take this opportunity to win him over.
この機に味方に引き入れるのだ
Take my East Palace seal and use my former identity
あなたは余の東宮の印を持ち
as the Crown Prince of the Eastern Palace to lure him in.
元東宮の名で奴を誘き寄せろ
Got it.
はい
As for Manager Yu...
では俞店主の方は？
Her?
あの女は
Just have someone keep a close eye on her.
見張るだけでいい
[Yixiang Restaurant]
[溢香楼]
Come on in, ladies. This way.
お二人様 こちらへどうぞ
Please come in, ladies.
お客様 どうぞ中へ
Welcome, ladies.
どうぞ お客様
Mrs. Fan.
樊姉さん
Changyu.
長玉
Come here.
こっちに来て
Look.
見て
The restaurant is so lively—
店がこんなににぎわってるのは
it's all thanks to you.
全部あなたのおかげよ
What do you mean, thanks to me?
私のおかげって？
Ever since your husband came by,
あなたの旦那さんが 溢香楼に来た後
that Qi fellow hasn't bothered me again.
斉という男に絡まれなくなった
I can finally focus on running the business.
おかげで商売に専念できるわ
Now look—the restaurant is so lively.
店がこんなににぎわってるのも
Of course it's thanks to you.
あなたのおかげじゃないか
Come with me.
こっちに来て
I wonder what Chef Li is cooking for New Year's Eve.
李料理長が大晦日に 何を作ったか知らないけど
What are you planning to eat tonight?
今夜は何を食べるの？
Cabbage and tofu,
白菜と豆腐の炒め
and stir-fried pork.
それと豚肉の炒め物
Go on.
行きなさい
Hello, Mother. Hello, Auntie Fan.
お母さん 樊叔母さん こんにちは
Sit.
座って
What is Changning doing at home?
長寧妹さんは家で何してるの？
I miss her.
会いたいよ
How about after New Year's Eve,
じゃあ大晦日が明けたら
you come over to our place and hang out with her?
うちに遊びに来たらどう？
Mother, can I go?
お母さん 行ってもいいの？
Fine.
いいわよ
Just this once.
今回だけよ
Changning said
長寧妹さんが言ったぞ
she'd show me her family heirloom.
先代から伝わるお宝を 見せてくれるって
Family heirloom?
先代から伝わるお宝
She probably meant our butcher knife.
彼女が言ったのは 豚屠りの包丁のことだね
I guess that won't be necessary.
それは別にいいでしょ
That's so cool!
最高じゃないか
So it's actually a butcher knife!
まさか豚屠りの包丁なんて
I have things to discuss with Auntie Fan.
樊叔母さんとは話があるから
Go study first.
先に勉強しなさい
Let's go.
行きましょう
Qianqian.
浅姉さん
Aren't you a bit too strict with Bao'er?
宝児に厳しすぎるんじゃない？
Not at all.
そんなことないわ
I just want him to succeed in life.
あの子の将来を思ってるだけよ
Changyu.
長玉
Tomorrow is New Year's Eve,
明日は大晦日だね
and you'll surely be swamped.
きっとすごく忙しいでしょう
I want to wish you in advance a smooth and happy year ahead.
来年も万事順調でありますように
I'm not a child.
子供じゃないのに
Why give me a lucky money pouch?
お年玉なんていらないわ
Us girls
私たち女の子は
are forever young.
いつになっても若いのよ
Come on. Let's get a drink.
さあ 飲みに行きましょう
Drinking at noon?
真昼間から飲むの？
We women drink when we feel like it,
女子がお酒を飲むのは 気分次第だわ
not when the clock says so.
時間なんて関係ない
If not now, then when?
今飲まないならいつ飲むというの？
[Overflowing Joy and Good Fortune]
[吉慶有余]
Cheers!
乾杯
Qianqian.
浅姉さん
The last time I was this happy
私が前回 こんなに楽しかったのは
was the day I married Yan Zheng.
言正と婚式を挙げた日よ
Changyu,
長玉
you've been married for quite some time now.
結婚してもうしばらく経ったけど
That husband of yours—
おうちの旦那さんは
are you satisfied with him?
どう？
He's not just all show, is he?
銀に見える白鑞の槍 じゃないでしょうね
All show?
銀に見える白鑞の槍じゃない
Yan Zheng is pure gold—
言正は金だわ
through and through.
本物の純金よ
He's that good?
そんなにすごいの？
I'm going to find someone
今から人を呼んで
to beat Granny Kang up.
あの康婆さんをぶん殴ってやる
She said you two hadn't even consummated your marriage.
あなたたちが初夜を迎えてないって 言ってたのよ
You were talking about consummating the marriage?
初夜の話だったの？
What else would I mean?
もちろん
Granny Kang really has a potty mouth.
康婆さんの肥溜め口
It's fine. I'll beat her up. I can afford the damages.
大丈夫 殴っても私が弁償できるわ
Don't worry.
心配しないで
Qianqian.
姉さん
Actually...
実は彼女
She wasn't entirely wrong.
全部が間違いってわけでもないの
Which part wasn't wrong?
どの部分が間違ってないの？
One day,
あの日
Mrs. Zhao locked the two of us in a room.
叔母さんが私と彼を 同じ部屋に閉じ込めたの
He probably wanted to kiss me.
彼は口付けをしたいはずだった
Did you eat tangerine peel candy?
陳皮飴を食べたの？
You smell like tangerine peel candy.
陳皮飴の香りがしてるが
Do you want some now?
君は今食べたいのか
And then?
それで？
Then...
それで
We had a fight.
喧嘩したの
So you two are actually serious?
本気だったの？
Actually, I know deep down
本当は分かってる
that
あの人は
he'd leave sooner or later.
いつかは離れていくってこと
I've hinted at it several times,
遠回しに何度も聞いたけど
yet he never gave a different answer.
考えを変えなかった
Your man does seem to be
あなたの旦那さん
too big a fish for your small pond.
確かにただ者じゃなさそうね
It's okay.
大丈夫
If he insists on leaving,
彼がどうしても行くと言うなら
just have a baby with him before he goes.
行く前に子供を作ってもらえばいい
Think about it—
考えてみて
if the child turns out as good-looking as him,
彼に似てる子を産んだら
that would be a kind of blessing too.
それも一種の幸せじゃないの？
That won't do, right?
それはダメでしょ
Wouldn't that basically be taking advantage of him?
まるでごろつきと同じよ
You know the saying, "you can't catch a wolf without sacrificing a lamb."
虎穴に入らずんば虎子を得ず
Wait—actually, in this case it's:
違う
you won't get a baby without feeding the wolf.
虎子を惜しめば虎穴に入れずよ
Don't worry.
安心して
Leave this to me.
この私に任せなさい
[Xigu Lane]
[西固巷]
Zhao Xun, the shopkeeper of Lin'an Rice Shop, is here to visit.
林安米屋の店主趙詢が 参上いたしました
It's freezing cold.
天気が寒くて
Won't Your Lordship invite me in?
侯爺は中へ誘ってくれませんか
Your Lordship.
侯爺
[Fill Your Belly]
[いっぱい食べる]
How did you recognize me?
なぜ私だとわかる？
I used to do business in Jizhou and Yanzhou.
私めは霽州と焉州で 商売をしておりまして
I was lucky enough to have seen Your Lordship there.
侯爺のお姿を 拝見したことがあります
So?
それで？
Why are you here today?
今日の用件は？
Your Xie family has always been loyal and virtuous,
謝家は代々忠義の家柄だと
which is a fact known throughout the whole country.
国全体で知らぬ者はおりません
Yet Heaven is unjust,
しかし天は非情にも
allowing evildoers to bring you harm.
奸臣に陥れさせてます
I too feel indignation on Your Lordship's behalf.
私めは侯爺のために 不平を鳴らしてます
I don't understand what you mean.
意味がわからない
Wasn't the reason Wei Yan hunted Your Lordship down
侯爺が魏厳に追われるのは
because you were investigating
十六年前の瑾州の惨事を
the Jinzhou Massacre from 16 years ago?
調べてたからでしょう
Who exactly are you?
一体何者だ？
[Chengde Heavenly Treasure]
[承德天宝]
Sixteen years ago,
十六年前
in that fire at the Eastern Palace—
東宮の火事で
I was one of the lucky survivors.
生き延びた者です
Wei Yan is a treacherous official in power,
奸臣の魏厳が権力を握り
supporting a puppet emperor.
傀儡の皇帝を立てました
We are a group of people
我らは
who want to restore order.
世を正そうとする者です
So,
それで？
do you have any proof?
証拠はある？
Crown Prince Chengde and Your Lordship's father
当時承德太子と尊父が
both died tragically in Jinzhou.
瑾州で共に非業の死を遂げました
Then the Emperor abdicated,
その後 皇帝が譲位し
and the Eastern Palace caught fire.
東宮が火事に見舞われました
All these suspicious events pointed to Wei Yan.
この不可解な出来事は 全て魏厳につながります
Your Lordship's father and the Crown Prince both died in battle,
尊父と太子は 戦場で共に命を落とし
and their bodies were hung on the city wall by the Beijue people for 3 days.
死体が北厥人に城楼に吊られて 三日も晒されました
Doesn't Your Lordship want to avenge this blood feud?
侯爺はこの血の恨みを 晴らしたくはないのですか
Your Lordship had just started reinvestigating the Jinzhou Massacre,
侯爺が瑾州の惨事を 再調査した途端に
and you immediately got hunted down
追われる身となり
and ended up here—
ここまで落ち延びました
isn't that proof enough?
これらが証拠になれないんですか
Not enough.
足らないんだ
We also found out that
その他に調べたところ
Wei Yan sent his Suicide Warriors
魏厳は配下の暗殺者を遣わし
across the Capital and 17 prefectures
一京十七府を走り回し
to kill over 10 people—
十数人を殺害しました
all retainers who once worked for Wei Yan
全部魏厳に仕えて
and later retired.
隠居した部下たちです
What exactly does the Fan family have
樊家には一体何があるんだ
that's worth the Wei family's Iron Suicide Warriors coming here for?
お前ら魏家の玄鉄暗殺者まで 動き出したなんて
It was the Prime Minister.
宰相様が
He sent me here to find a letter.
書状を探せと
So Fan Erniu must have also worked for Wei Yan before,
つまり樊二も 魏厳のために働いたから
which is why he kept being hunted down.
何度も追われていたな
Your Lordship.
侯爺
Wei Yan is immensely powerful now,
魏厳の勢いは絶大で
with ambitions that could overshadow the heavens.
天下を覆わんとしています
To bring him down,
奴を倒すのに
doesn't Your Lordship need an ally?
侯爺は手駒が要りませんか
How can I trust you?
どうすればあなたを信用できるのか
How can Your Lordship trust me?
どうすれば侯爺は 信じてれくれますか
Give me a deposit first.
まずは手付金を払ってくれ
What deposit?
どんな手付金ですか？
200,000 piculs of grain—
二十万石の穀物は
how does that sound?
いかがかな？
It seems he really knows about
やはり奴は知っているな
my grain collection from all across Jizhou and Chongzhou.
余が霽州や崇州から 兵糧を徴収していること
We bought from many sources,
我らは多方面から買い付けており
with over 100 grain merchants involved.
穀商だけ 百人も関わっているのに
How did he know so accurately?
なぜ正確に知っているんですか
I'd actually like to ask you that.
それについて 余はあなたに聞きたいが
Forgive me, Master. It was my negligence.
お許しをください この私の不手際です
But it's good that he's willing to name his terms.
だが条件を出してきたのは好都合だ
It's business, after all.
商談というのは
Once he quotes a price, we can talk.
値が付いてこそ始まるものだ
200,000 piculs...
二十万石ですよ
Master,
館様
the grain from all across Chongzhou and Jizhou
ここ数か月 崇州と霽州の兵糧は
has almost been emptied by us these past months.
ほぼ我らで買い占めております
He didn't ask you to give it all at once, did he?
一度に渡せとは言ってない
Father never cared about me,
父王は余を気にかけたことはなく
and the position of Crown Prince was meant for Sui Yuanqing.
世子の座も随元青のものだ
But if we can gain the support of the Marquis of Wu'an,
だが武安侯の助力が得られれば
our chances of success will soar.
我らの勝算は大きくなるぞ
What if the Marquis of Wu'an
もし武安侯が
doesn't believe your identity,
館様の身分を信じず
takes the grain, and turns against us, Master?
兵糧を奪った後 すぐ裏切った場合
What then?
どうなさるおつもりですか
Turn against us?
裏切る？
Who else can he turn to?
奴には行く当てがある？
Can he possibly go back to work for Wei Yan?
再び魏厳の配下になれると思う？
As long as he's willing to help me wholeheartedly,
奴が心から余を助けるなら
let alone 200,000 piculs of grain—
二十万石どころか
I can even grant all 4 prefectures
西北四府すべてを
of the Northwest to him as his fief.
奴の封地として与えてもよい
Understood.
わかりました
I'll see to it immediately.
ではすぐに手配します
Wei Yan, oh Wei Yan.
魏厳よ
You will soon
お前はまもなく
be bitten by the ungrateful wolf
自ら育てた恩知らずに
you raised yourself.
噛み付かれることになるぞ
Prime Minister.
宰相様
I was investigating Grand Tutor Li's dealings with the rebels,
李太傅と賊党の件を 密かに調べてた時
and I accidentally found out that when the Marquis of Wu'an
偶然にも
was reinvestigating the Jinzhou cases from 16 years ago,
武安侯が十六年前の 瑾州の件を再調査したのは
it was exactly Lord Changxin's people who plotted against him.
長信王府の者の仕業と判明しました
If Xie Zheng didn't exist in this world,
この世に謝征がいなければ
Lord Changxin would have one less major threat on the battlefield.
長信王にとって最大の脅威が消える
The Sui family is
随家は
trying to ruin my great plans.
私の事を邪魔してる
There's one more thing.
もう一つ
Li Huai'an was recalled to the Capital by Grand Tutor Li
李懐安が李太傅に 京へ呼び戻されました
for some unknown reason.
理由は不明です
With Princess Royal back in the Capital,
長公主が都に戻られた
that old coot probably wants to push the marriage,
あの老いぼれは 縁談をまとめるため
so he hurried to recall his eldest legitimate grandson.
嫡長孫を急いで呼び戻したのだ
Just leave him be.
放っておけ
Write to He Jingyuan immediately
すぐに賀敬元に手紙を送れ
and tell him to defend Lucheng to the death.
盧城を死守させろ
That's the place for the decisive battle.
そこが勝負を決める地だ
[New Year's Eve]
[大晦日]
Happy New Year.
あけましておめでとう
Come on, everyone, time for dinner.
さあ 食事だよ
Coming. Coming.
来たわ
Happy New Year, Mrs. Wang.
王叔母さん あけましておめでとう
Happy New Year, Mrs. San.
三娘がご挨拶しました
Happy New Year, Mr. San.
三叔父さん あけましておめでとう
Happy New Year.
おめでとう
[Chunfeng Tofu Shop]
[春風豆腐坊]
Happy New Year to you.
新年のご挨拶です
Keep writing. Keep writing.
もっと書いて
Horizontal.
横
Horizontal, vertical.
横縦
Vertical.
縦
Horizontal with a turn, left-falling, right-falling.
横 折れ 払い
Sister, Zheng is teaching me how to write.
お姉ちゃん 義兄さんが 私に字を教えてる
Good girl.
いい子だね
Do you know how to write Spring Festival couplets?
春聯は書ける？
My mother used to write them every year.
今までの春聯は母が書いてたの
Can you write Spring Festival couplets, Zheng?
義兄さんは春聯を書ける？
Get me the paper.
紙を持ってきて
Okay.
はい
You ground too much ink.
墨を磨りすぎた
♪ The scenery is as clear as me ♪
♪ 清らかな山と川 私のよう ♪
Then write a few more pairs.
なら何枚か多く書こう
We can give some to Mrs. Zhao and the others,
叔母さんたちに何枚渡して
♪ With very pale colors ♪
♪ 淡く色づけて ♪
and we can put the rest on the doorframes of all these rooms.
残りは各部屋の入り口に貼って
♪ Just like the outline in the mirror ♪
♪ 鏡に映る姿のように ♪
For good omen.
めでたいだよね
♪ I think that's me, being naive ♪
♪ それが何も知らない私なの ♪
Alright.
わかった
♪ Unlocking my heart ♪
♪ そっと心を閉じ込めて ♪
♪ I hid you in my soul ♪
♪ あなたを 私の魂に閉じ込めて ♪
♪ The moon is as quiet as me ♪
♪ この月の光は穏やかに 私のよう ♪
♪ The light shines ♪
♪ 光が差し込んで ♪
♪ It illuminates the turbulence in my heart ♪
♪ 胸に隠した傷を照らす ♪
[Sprouting Grass]
[草芽生]
♪ It seems to be the fire of love ♪
♪ まるで愛の炎のよう♪
♪ Just a few sparks ♪
♪ ほんの少しだけでも ♪
♪ Let me hide in your heart ♪
♪ あなたの心に隠れさせて ♪
♪ I pray that our love ♪
♪ 私たちの愛を願うよ ♪
♪ Will never end ♪
♪ ずっと離れないで ♪
♪ It's worth my foolishly waiting ♪
♪ 私は一生をかけても ♪
♪ For a lifetime ♪
♪ 待つことを悔やまない ♪
♪ Clear and quiet as me ♪
♪ 清らかな私 穏やかな私 ♪
D-Did I accidentally touch you?
あっ ごめん ぶつかった？
It's fine. I just got a bit too much ink on the brush.
大丈夫 墨をつけすぎただけ
♪ So what if we encounter difficulties? ♪
♪ 棘があっても構わない ♪
♪ I pray that our love will not be like sand ♪
♪ 私は愛を願うよ ♪
♪ Slipping into the sea ♪
♪ 砂が海に 沈むようにはならないで ♪
[Be a Good Person]
[いい人になれ]
♪ I'd rather use this life ♪
♪ 私はこの一生をかけても ♪
Your calligraphy is really good.
よく書いたね
♪ To guard our love forever ♪
♪ 長く愛を守りたいの ♪
♪ Clear and quiet as me ♪
♪ 清らかな私 穏やかな私 ♪
What a pity.
もったいないわ
But it's okay.
でも大丈夫
♪ Why do we need to seek cause and effect ♪
♪ どうして因果を求めるの ♪
[As ice thaws, the springs awaken] [With snow gone, new grass sprouts]
[冰銷泉脉動 雪尽草芽生]
I'll just put this pair on the door of Changning's and my room.
私と寧娘の部屋の入り口に 貼ればいいもの
Ice something...
氷とか何とか
Spring something something...
泉とか何とか
Snow something... New grass sprouts.
雪...草 芽生
As ice thaws, the springs awaken.
「冰銷泉脉動」 (注:氷が溶けて　泉脈も動き)
With snow gone, new grass sprouts.
「雪尽草芽生」 (注:雪が消えて　草が芽生え)
When my mother wrote Spring Festival couplets,
母も昔春聯を書いた時
she didn't like writing those
ありふれた縁起のいい言葉が
clichéd auspicious phrases either.
好きではなかった
Do you like these?
気に入ってる？
[Be a Good Person]
[いい人になれ]
You know how to paint?
絵も描けるの？
Only a little.
少しだけ
That's enough.
それだけでも十分よ
If you go and sell your calligraphy and paintings out there,
書画を売ったら
you'll definitely make a lot of money.
大儲けできるはず
I don't paint what doesn't please me.
気に入らない絵を描かない
I want to write something too.
私も書きたい
Write a top scroll then.
じゃあ横額を書いて
Come on, Changning, write a top scroll.
さあ 寧娘 横額を書いて
What should you write?
何を書くの？
Just write this.
これを書こう
[You'll Be Rich]
[一定有銭] (注:金持ちになりますように)
How's this top scroll?
この横額はどう？
Just like...
まさに
Joining a dog's tail to sable fur.
尻すぼみのようだ
[You'll Be Rich]
[一定有銭]
That means it's very good, right?
すごく良いという意味でしょ
It's perfect.
ちょうどいい
[You'll Be Rich]
[一定有銭]
I wrote it too well.
私が上手すぎるわね
I'm amazing.
すごいね
Oh right, we're missing the falcon.
そうだ 隼隼がまだだ
Good falcon,
隼隼 いい子ね
let's celebrate the New Year together.
一緒に新年を祝おう
With the falcon's claw print,
隼隼の足形の捺印を押して
our family is complete.
家族が揃ったね
[You'll Be Rich]
[一定有銭]
Look.
ほら
Dear.
あなた
Lower. Lower.
もっと下へ
Alright, alright. Right there.
そこだ
Don't move. Don't move further. That's it.
動かすな そこだ
-Alright. -Let's go check on Changyu.
- いいわ - 長玉のところに行ってみて
Okay.
ええ
Dear.
嫁よ
How is the calligraphy?
この字はどうだ？
It's beautiful.
なんてきれいな字
-I've never seen such nice calligraphy before. -He wrote this, right?
- こんなきれいな字を 見たことがない - 彼が書いたものだよね
-I guess so. -You're illiterate. Can you really understand it?
- そうよね - 字も読めないお前もわかる？
I may not be able to read,
字が読めないけど
but I can tell this calligraphy is valuable.
この字なら高く売れると分かるわ
Look how square and upright the characters are.
ほら この字は堂々として
So neat and proper.
きっちりしてる
It's obvious it's worth a fortune.
見れば値打ちがあるとすぐ分かるわ
Mr. Zhao, Mrs. Zhao.
老趙 趙叔母さん
The couplets are written so well.
見事な対聯だわ
Who wrote these?
誰が書いたの？
Changyu's husband wrote all of these.
これは全部長玉の 旦那さんが書いたわ
Changyu's husband.
長玉の旦那さん
Changyu,
長玉
your husband writes really nice couplets—
旦那さんが書いた対聯は 本当に見事だね
even better than the ones Scholar Song
例年の宋挙人が書いたものより
wrote in previous years.
ずっといいわ
That's why I say
だから言ったでしょ
our Changyu has good taste.
長玉は人見る目があるって
Can he write a pair for me too?
私にも一枚書いてくれない？
-Yeah. Write a pair for us too. -Write for all of us.
- そうよ　私たちにも書いてよ - そうよ　皆に
Sis.
皆さん
I'm sorry.
ごめんね
We ran out of red paper for the couplets.
家に春聯用の紙がもうないわ
Oh, red paper for the couplets?
春聯用の紙なら
I've got plenty of red paper at home from previous years.
うちには赤い紙がたくさんあるわ
I've got some at home too.
うちにもあるよ
-I have some too. -Me too.
- 私も - うちにもあるわ
Alright.
分かった
Bring the paper over.
紙を持ってきてくれ
Alright!
はいよ
Quick, go get the red paper.
早く赤い紙を取りに行きな
Okay, thanks.
ええ ありがとう
See you in a bit.
じゃあ また後で
Let's go.
行こう
If you aren't willing,
もし嫌なら
you didn't have to agree.
引き受けなくてもいいわ
Don't worry about me.
私に気を使わなくてもいい
I am willing.
嫌ではない
You just said
さっきは言ったんじゃない
you wouldn't paint what didn't please you.
気に入らない絵は描かないと
Now it pleases you?
今は気に入った
Grind the ink.
墨をすってくれ
Changyu.
長玉
Mrs. Zhuang.
庄姉さん
Here's some homemade puffed rice candy—
手作りのおこし
a little snack for Changning.
寧児のおやつにしよう
But...
これは...
Take it.
受け取って
Changyu, I heard your husband was writing Spring Festival couplets for people.
長玉　旦那さんが 春聯を書いてるって聞いて
Our family hasn't gotten ours written yet, either,
うちもまだ書いてなかったから
so I boldly came along.
厚かましくも来ちゃった
It's nothing fancy,
大したものじゃないけど
just some freshly ground tofu for you to taste.
出来上がったばかりの 豆腐を持ってきた
Ladies,
皆さん
please have a seat first.
どうぞ座ってください
Alright, alright.
はい
Thank you.
ありがとう
Here's the red paper I brought.
赤い紙を持ってきたわ
Alright, thank you.
どうも ありがとう
Harmony brings peace to all frontiers.
家和自秀三辺静 (注:家が和せば　万事がうまくいく)
Done.
よし
It's finished.
できたぞ
"Lanterns shine on homes to celebrate the prosperous year."
灯籠照户慶余年 (注:灯りが家を照らし　余歳を祝う)
"The ox carries spring to plow the green fields."
牛背駄春耕緑野 (注:牛背に春を乗せて　緑の野を耕す)
It means that when spring comes next year,
来年の春になれば
there will be a bumper harvest,
五穀豊穣の上に
and the whole family will be happy and healthy.
家族が皆幸せであります ようにと言う意味だ
Though storm and darkness fill the sky
風雨晦き朝に
and the rooster crows without end,
鳴く鶏
now that I have met you—
我が君見れば
how could my heart not rejoice?
喜び溢る
The meaning of this poem line is that
この詩の意味は
amidst the gloom and pouring rain,
暗く激しい雨が降りしきる中
the roosters crow in panic.
鶏の鳴き声が不安げに響いてる
Yet, precisely in this chaotic moment,
そんな混沌とした状況の中で
I glance around,
ふと目をやると
and I catch sight of her.
彼女が目に入った
It's like parting the clouds and mist,
その瞬間 まるで雲をかき分けるように
and a beam of light falls upon me—
一筋の光が私を照らした
warm and radiant,
体中は温かい光に満ち
filling my heart with joy.
心は喜びに満たされた
When I heard him recite this line before,
前に彼がこの言葉を読んでくれた時
I just thought it sounded nice,
耳心地がいいとは思っただけで
but I had no idea what was so good about it.
どこがいいか分からなかった
Until just now,
さっきまで
when he turned his head and looked at me.
彼が振り向いて私を見た
In that instant,
その瞬間
the courtyard fell completely silent.
庭が急に静かになった
Even the falling snow seemed lighter,
舞い落ちてる雪も 軽くなった気がした
and even the wind blowing over
吹き渡した風でさえ
felt softer and gentler.
柔らかくなり 肌を刺さないようになった
It was like the sun on the Winter Solstice—
まるで冬至の日のように
neither slanting nor skewed,
まっすぐに
shining perfectly on me.
私を照らしてるようだ
It turns out when you are truly happy,
人は本当にうれしく思う時
your heart sings.
心が鳴るものだよね
Just like when you sit by the stove,
かまどで火にあたる時
and the firewood crackles softly,
薪がパチパチと立った音みたい
crisp and warm.
ささやかで暖かい
Your hand must hurt, right?
手が痛むでしょう
It's nothing.
大丈夫
Still toughing it out.
口硬いね
Are you here for couplets too?
あなたも対聯を書きに来たの？
Before...
昔は
Before, it was always my elder grandson, Kang Dan, who wrote the Spring Festival couplets.
長孫の康胆が書いてた
But later, he got into trouble
その後 律法を犯して
and was sent off for forced labor.
労役に出されてしまった
After that,
それで
Scholar Song helped out.
宋挙人が助けてくださった
You see, Kang Dan turned 18 this year.
康胆は今年で十八歳になるが
He's timid and simple-minded.
気が弱く愚鈍でな
I just hope
だから
that my younger grandson, Xiaohu,
末孫の小虎は
could be smarter and sharper than his older brother.
兄より賢くなってほしいと願ってる
You know,
人というものは
by the end of the year,
一年中
isn't life really just about having something to look forward to?
希望を頼りに生きるものだ
Next year, or the year after—
来年 再来年と
perhaps
きっと
things will get better.
よくなるかも
Please sit.
座って
What do you want me to write?
何を書きたい？
Just no more wars,
もう戦は起こらないでほしい
so that our Kang family
私の康家に
could continue our line.
跡継ぎを残してほしい
And I hope my two grandsons,
あの二人の孫が
without their parents to protect them,
親がいなくても
could still grow up safe and sound.
無事に育ちますように
Okay.
分かった
[Composed]
[従容有致]
[Ornamented Beauty]
[鉛華]
Greetings, Mother.
母上にご挨拶をいたします
May I ask why
母上が私をお呼びになったのは
you summoned me here, Mother?
いかなるご用件でしょうか
It's New Year's Eve, a time for family reunion.
大晦日は一家団らんの日なのに
Do I really need a reason
母さんがそなたに会うのに
just to see you?
口実が必要だとでも？
That's not what I meant.
そういう意味ではありません
I wish you a prosperous New Year, Mother.
母上がよき新年を迎えられ
May peace and health be with you always.
安寧と健勝に恵まれますように 願っております
You were betrothed to the Marquis of Wu'an since birth.
そなたは武安侯とは 幼き頃からの許嫁で
Back when the Marquis of Wu'an was still around,
武安侯がご存命の頃は
he was a heroic young man with great military merits.
若くして勇ましく 戦功も赫々たるだった
Such a fine man would have been a great match for you,
あのような立派な若君こそ 良き伴侶であったのに
yet you said you only saw him as an older brother
そなたは兄妹の情しかないと
and refused to take him as your Prince Consort.
駙馬に迎えることを拒んだ
And now, this failed scheme
今ではたかが一つの盤面に
has consumed you.
心を奪われたとは
What do you mean by that, Mother?
母上 それはどういう意味ですか
Ever since you returned to the palace,
そなたが帰宮してから
you've used illness as an excuse multiple times to put off meeting Li Huai'an.
何度も病気を口実にして 李懐安との面会を先延ばした
I have already made arrangements.
私が既に手配した
You will go to the Lantern Festival with him on the fifteenth.
上元節に彼と灯籠祭りに行きなさい
Mother!
母上
The Gongsun family has been barred from holding office in the court for generations.
公孫家は代々入閣を許されない
This is an imperial regulation
これは皇家の定めで
and must never be defied.
決して逆らってはならない
As the Princess Royal,
長公主たるそなたが
you must not let that scheme
あの盤面で皇家の大業を
ruin the grand cause of our imperial family.
台無しにしてはならない
I'm not your pawn, Mother.
私は母上の駒ではございません
And I refuse to be manipulated in this palace scheme.
宮廷という盤面の上で 弄ばれたくはないのです
You only care about family glory
母上の心には一族の栄光と
and imperial regulations, Mother.
皇家の定めしかありません
Have you ever truly cared about my happiness or sorrow?
私の喜びや悲しみに関心を 持ったことがありますか
In short, from now on,
とにかくこれからは
you must not see anyone from the Gongsun family again.
公孫家の者に一切会ってはならない
Just cut that thought off now.
早いうちにその念を断ちなさい
If there's nothing else, Mother,
母上はもし他に御用がなければ
I shall take my leave.
これにて失礼いたします
Shu!
姝児
Your Highness, where are you going?
長公主様 どちらに向かいますか
[Ornamented Beauty]
[鉛華]
I'm going to hang myself.
首を吊りに行くの
Do you want to join me, Nanny?
ばあやも付き合ってくるの？
[Composed]
[従容有致]
Though loved for its clever words,
人は甘言に心を動かされど
the bird yearns to fly free.
鳥は空を恋い飛び立つ
Come on.
食べよう
Let's eat.
さあ 食べて
It smells so good.
いい香りだ
Smells so good.
いい香りね
Thank you. Thank you.
ありがとう
Here.
ほら
Yummy, yummy.
うまい
Yummy.
おいしい
Eat up.
早く食べて
It's so good.
うまいぞ
Coming up.
はい
-Happy New Year!
- あけましておめでとう
Let's have another cup.
もう一杯飲もう
Fill it up.
注いで
I want some too.
私にも
No, you're still injured.
だめよ ケガしてるでしょ
This light liquor won't hurt.
このどぶろくなら平気よ
Have some tea instead.
お茶を飲んで
The doctor said
医者が言ったわ
no alcohol until you recover.
完全に治るまで 酒を飲んじゃだめだと
I want some too.
私も飲みたい
Changning, you can't drink either.
寧娘もだめよ
Come on, have tea with Zheng.
ほら 義兄さんとお茶にしましょ
Eat and drink well. Peace year after year.
よく食べ よく飲み 災ない一年を
Cheers.
飲もう
Come on.
さあ
Yan Zheng.
言正
Why don't we...
私たちが...
Fireworks!
花火が上がったぞ
Let's go watch the fireworks.
花火を見に行こう
Come on, let's go watch the fireworks.
行こう行こう 花火を見よう
Be careful, Changning.
寧娘 気をつけて
What did you just say?
さっき何を言った？
I didn't catch that.
はっきり聞こえなかった
I... I said I wanted to drink more.
いや まだ酒を飲みたいと
-Come on, let's go upstairs. -Let's go upstairs and watch.
- 行こう　階上へ - 上で見よう
Good wine.
いい酒よ
Don't drink too much.
飲みすぎないで
I'm perfectly sober.
しっかりしてるわ
This wine isn't strong at all.
こんな酒じゃ酔わないよ
I'll pour you some tea.
お茶を注いだ
Sober up with some tea.
お茶を飲んで 酔いを覚まして
Looking down on me, huh?
誰をなめてるの？
My father can drink a whole jar of strong liquor,
父は白酒を一瓶飲めるよ
so I can handle at least half a jar.
私だって最低半瓶は飲めるわ
This wine isn't intoxicating at all.
この酒じゃ全然酔わない
Come on, bottoms up.
さあ 乾杯
Come on.
ほら
You really are drunk.
本当に酔ってるぞ
I'm totally fine.
平気よ
Happy New Year.
新年おめでとう
You won't get a baby
虎子を惜しめば
without feeding the wolf.
虎穴に入れずよ
What baby?
何の虎穴？